RG 009:004, Connecticut vs. Massachusetts
Connecticut State Library
On February 18, 1930 hearings started before special master Charles W. Bunn at the Five-Cents Savings Bank building in Boston, Massachusetts. Connecticut argued the diversion of the rivers would affect the flow of the Connecticut River and the underway diversion project if not challenged by Connecticut might lead Massachusetts to take water using established precedent. The special master on the opening day of testimony limited the scope of the hearing to the "facts pertaining to the Ware and Swift river projects."40 The first witness called by Connecticut at the hearing was Chief Engineer Frank E. Winsor of the Metropolitan District Water Supply Commission.41 The beginning of the hearing brought to light the inability to get data from Massachusetts that Connecticut claimed existed. The special master suggested rival engineers work together to find the data Connecticut claimed existed in some state departments of Massachusetts. The hearing was recessed until February 25 in order for engineers to find data requested by counsel for Connecticut.42 Rival engineers over the recess discovered the data in several state departments of Massachusetts on which legislation was based for diversion of the Ware River and Swift River.43 The hearing then went on to take testimony from experts on pollution.
The hearing was moved from Boston to the County Building in Hartford on March 3, 1930. Local farmers, with land next to the river, were called by counsel for Connecticut to testify before the special master on how flooding from the Connecticut River fertilized their crop land. James A. Foord, from the Massachusetts Agricultural College at Amherst, assisted Massachusetts counsel during cross-examination of the farmers.44 On March 5, counsel for Connecticut presented a new argument at the hearing suggesting that Boston get its water supply from the Merrimac River instead of the Connecticut River watershed. Massachusetts special attorney Bentley W. Warren in response submitted a "formal objection to the introduction of evidence bearing on the available supply of water other than that contemplated by the metropolitan district." Warren also filed a motion asking that the case be dismissed without prejudice on the grounds Connecticut failed to show substantial damages that would be caused by diversion of water from the Connecticut River and "failed to sustain the burden of proof." The special master noted the objection and felt the motion would be appropriate only after all evidence was heard in the case.45 The examination of witnesses and arguments before the special master concluded on April 24, 1930 in St. Paul, Minnesota.46
The special master in his report recommended to the Supreme Court that Connecticut's bill of complaint be dismissed and "the decree contain a provision for the protection of the owner of the [King's Island] dam and power at that place."47 The Supreme Court on May 26, 1930 ordered the special master's report filed with the court and the parties were required to file exceptions and objections to the report on or before October 6, 1930.48 Connecticut submitted seventy five exceptions to the special master's report. Massachusetts did not object to the report.
The Supreme Court on January 5-6, 1931 heard oral arguments on the exceptions to the special master's report. On February 24 the court ruled against granting Connecticut an injunction prohibiting Massachusetts from diverting water and dismissed Connecticut's bill of complaint. The court ruled Connecticut retained the right to bring legal action against Massachusetts at any time if water increases appeared to occur outside legislation passed by Massachusetts and the authority of the War Department. The court also ruled that each side pay its own legal costs and one half the expenses and compensation of the special master. Counsel for Massachusetts and Connecticut was ordered by the court to prepare a form of decree in agreement with the decision. The Supreme Court on March 23, 1931 issued the decree deciding the case in Massachusetts favor.
The Connecticut vs. Massachusetts case cost the State of Connecticut over $300,000 not including half the costs of the special master. Attorney General Benjamin W. Alling, in the Sixteenth Biennial Report of the Attorney General, on the case said, "If the State of Connecticut had permitted this first taking to occur without a contest, a precedent would have been established for future takings of an unlimited amount. The action by our State has preserved our rights and limited the diversion of water to portions of the flood flows of the Ware and Swift Rivers only, with the right preserved to interfere with additional efforts to increase this amount to the prejudice of our citizens."49 The Swift River and Ware River water diversion project was completed on August 14, 1939 with the first water flowing into the Quabbin Reservoir.50
Endnotes
1 L.D.G. Bentley, "Plan Study of All Water Sources," Boston Daily Globe, June 29, 1919, p. 40.
2 Boston Daily Globe, January 29, April 9, May 4, May 19, 1922; May 11, 1924.
3 Boston Daily Globe, May 14-15, 1924.
4 "Towns to Discuss Ware River Project," Boston Daily Globe, November 11, 1925, p. 16.
5 "$71,200,000 Needed for Water System," Boston Daily Globe, December 1, 1925, p. A4.
6 "$27,500,000 Asked for More Reservoirs," Boston Daily Globe, December 2, 1925, p. 11.
7 "Engineers Work for Water Bill," Boston Daily Globe, April 9, 1926, p. 22
8 Ibid.
9 Answer of Defendant before Supreme Court of the United States, p. 34, box 341, folder Conn[ecticut] River & Mass[achusetts] Ware & Swift Rivers, Office of the Governor: John Harper Trumbull Records, RG 005:025, Connecticut State Library.
10 "Field Work for New Water Supply Starts," Boston Daily Globe, November 4, 1926, p. A19.
11 "Swift Valley Bill is Given Committee," Boston Daily Globe, February 9, 1927, p. 2.
12 Answer of Defendant before Supreme Court of the United States, p. 48, box 341, folder Conn[ecticut] River & Mass[achusetts] Ware & Swift Rivers, Office of the Governor: John Harper Trumbull Records, RG 005:025, Connecticut State Library.
13 box 299, folder 35, Office of the Governor: Charles A. Templeton Records, RG 005:024, Connecticut State Library.
14 box 309, folder Attorney General's Opinions, Office of the Governor: John Harper Trumbull Records, RG 005:025, Connecticut State Library.
15 box 309, folder Attorney General's Opinions, Office of the Governor: John Harper Trumbull Records, RG 005:025, Connecticut State Library.
16 box 312, folder Connecticut River - Mass. Rivers Special Investigation by Caleb M. Saville, Office of the Governor: John Harper Trumbull Records, RG 005:025, Connecticut State Library.
17 box 341, folder Waterways - Conn[ecticut] River & Mass[achusetts] Ware & Swift Rivers, Office of the Governor: John Harper Trumbull Records, RG 005:025, Connecticut State Library.
18 box 6, folder 4, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
19 box 6, folder 4, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
20 box 341, folder Waterways - Conn[ecticut] River & Mass[achusetts] Ware & Swift Rivers, Office of the Governor: John Harper Trumbull Records, RG 005:025, Connecticut State Library.
21 Hartford Courant, December 28, 1927.
22 box 6, folder 4, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
23 Motion for Leave to File Bill in Equity Bill of Complaint, 1928, p. 14-15, box 8, folder 28, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
24 276 U.S. 588
25 Worcester (Mass.) Gazette, January 26, 1928, box 8, folder 16, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
26 Holyoke (Mass.) Transcript, January 31, 1928, box 8, folder 16, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
27 Worcester (Mass.) Gazette, February 10, 1928, box 8, folder 15, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
28 Hartford Times, February 10, 1928, box 8, folder 15, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
29 Bristol (Conn.) Press, March 5, 1928, box 8, folder 14, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
30 Hartford Times, March 6, 1928, box 8, folder 14, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
31 Norwich Bulletin, March 15, 1928, box 8, folder 14, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
32 Springfield News, March 14, 1928, box 8, folder 14, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
33 Bulkley S. Griffin, "Down Washington Way," Hartford Courant, December 28, 1928, p. 2.
34 "Chicago Drainage Decision Seen as Encouraging Here," Hartford Courant, January 15, 1929, p. 30.
35 Bulkley S. Griffin, "Plan to Wait Court Ruling on Diversion," Hartford Courant, February 7, 1929, p. 1.
36 50 S.Ct. 84
37 "State Board Blocks River Compromise," Hartford Courant, December 7, 1929, p. 2.
38 280 U.S. 532, 50 S.Ct. 158
39 Bulkley S. Griffin, "Bay State Wins Point in Diversion," Hartford Courant, January 21, 1930, p. 2.
40 "Bay State Scores Point in River Case," Worcester Telegram, February 19, 1930, box 8, folder 18, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
41 "Mass.-Connecticut Legal Battle Over Water Opens," Boston Traveler, February 18, 1930, box 8, folder 18, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
42 "For Conciliation in River Dispute," Hartford Times, February 22, 1930, box 8, folder 18, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
43 "Get Much Data On Swift River," Hartford Times, February 24, 1930, box 8, folder 18, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
44 "Diversion Dispute Now in Hartford," Manchester (Conn.) Herald, March 3, 1930, box 8, folder 18, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
45 "State Suggests Boston Utilize Merrimac River," Hartford Times, March 5, 1930, box 8, folder 18, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
46
box 1-2, transcript volumes, Office of the Attorney General: Connecticut vs. Massachusetts Records, RG 009:004, Connecticut State Library.
47 282 U.S. 660, 51 S.Ct. 286, p. 6
48 50 S.Ct. 459
49 Connecticut Office of the Attorney General, Sixteenth Biennial Report of the Attorney General for the Two Years Ended January 7, 1931 (Hartford: State of Connecticut, 1931), 32.
50 Massachusetts Water Resources Authority, (accessed September 13, 2010).
Scope and Content
The records were arranged into fourteen series which document the Connecticut vs. Massachusetts court case. The series include Transcripts, Exhibits, Draft Case Preparation Binders, Reports, Enginnering Studies, Stenographic Notebooks, War Department Materials, Correspondence, Subject Files, Legislative Files, Press Files, Printed Documents, Invoices, and Maps.
Series 1. Transcripts, 1930-1931, consist of eight volumes of testimony before Special Master Charles W. Bunn. The series also includes a index to volumes of testimony, a name index, a consolidated index to exhibits, qualifications of experts, corrections to testimony, oral arguments before the United States Supreme Court, and rebuttals.
Series 2. Exhibits, 1929-1930, include an indexed volume of complaintant and defendants exhibits. The series also consists of a consolidated index of exhibits and lose copies of exhibits C-36, C-39, and D-21. The miscellaneous file contains lose copies of exhibit 7 and headings with exhibit numbers with brief descriptions of how the exhibit supports the complaintants arguments.
Series 3. Draft Case Preparation Binders, 1930, consist of eight different subject arguments made by the state with a summary of each side's expert witness' testimony using applicable potions of the testimony transcripts for each argument. The subject areas of argument are: massachusetts project, navigation, power, agriculture, pollution, fish life, available supplies, and stream flow.
Series 4. Reports, 1890-1930, include eight different chapters drafted by Morris Knowles, Incorporated for the Attorney General's Office on various subjects. The subjects include: analysis of legislation, stream flows, diversion from Connecticut River tributaries, pollution, fish life, necessity for additional metropolitan water supplies, and supplies in Eastern Massachusetts. The series also consists of a survey of the Connecticut River and tributaries south of Holyoke, Massachusetts; studies comparing the cost of construction, collection, treatment, and transmission projects of water in Eastern Massachusetts; annual reports of the Metropolitan Water and Sewerage Board and the Commonwealth of Massachusetts Metropolitan District Commmission; Massachusetts annual health reports; and state of Connecticut quality of Merrimac River water progress reports one through four.
Series 5. Engineering Studies, 1928-1930, include fourteen binder volumes of engineering studies produced by Morris Knowles, Incorporated for the state of Connecticut. The subjects of the studies include: stream flow, navigation, power, pollution, fish life, ground water, agriculture, water needs of Boston, and Eastern Massachusetts supplies.
Series 6. Stenographic Notebooks, undated, are unidentified as to date or subject matter.
Series 7. War Department Materials, 1922-1929, consist of a brief filed with the War Department; a public hearing transcript on granting a permit to the Massachussetts Metropolitan District Water Supply Commission; a motion to the Supreme Court of the United States requesting an injunction against the War Department and to subpoena the Secretary of War, Chief of Engineers, and agents to answer allegations; documents relating to naviagation on the Connecticut River; and exhibits relating to the actions of the War Department.
Series 8. Correspondence, 1922-1931, include seventeen folders of correspondence between the Attorney General's Office and attorneys; law firms; Charles W. Bunn, Special Master; Commonwealth of Massachusetts; state of New Jersey; Chicago Sanitary District; Morris Knowles, Incorporated; state of Connecticut Highway Department; Connecticut State Water Commission; Clerk of the United States Supreme Court; and War Department.
Series 9. Subject Files, circa 1900-1932, consist of materials related to the case on various topics such as agriculture; case law and precedent; case notes; legal documents; related cases; riparian rights; supporting documents; War Department; and water policy of the state of Connecticut. The miscellaneous files contain drafts of documents; figures and tables; related legal cases and citations; and general research for the case.
Series 10. Legislative Files, 1908-1929, include bill files from the General Court of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts; state of Connecticut House of Representatives; and the United States Congress. The bill files of the General Court of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts contain reports from the Metropolitan District Water Supply Commission, State Board of Health, the Department of Public Health, commission on additional water supply, the special commission appointed to investigate, and joint standing committee on water supply; committee reports; acts; and members remarks. The bill files of the state of Connecticut House of Representatives contain an act authorizing Hartford and New Britain to enter into contracts concerning water supplies. The federal bill files contain bills, reports, public acts, and joint resolutions on river and water related issues. The miscellaneous bill file contains a proposed resolution for the city of New London to furnish the United States with land for a Coast Guard Academy and a copy of an act making additional provisions for the Metropolitan District Water Supply Commission to divert water from the Swift River.
Series 11. Press Files, 1926-1930, contain newspaper clippings and articles about the case.
Series 12. Printed Documents, 1919-1931, include briefs, motions, oral arguments, and materials from related cases used by the Attorney General's office in support of the state's arguments.
Series 13. Invoices, 1928-1931, contain copies of invoices paid by the Attorney General's Office, the State Department of Health, and the State Water Commission in connection with water diversion litigation.
Series 14. Maps, circa 1913-1930, consist of maps that document the proposed water diversion from the Swift and Ware rivers which are tributaries of the Connecticut River.
Arrangement
Series 1. Transcripts, 1930-1931
Series 2. Exhibits, 1929-1930
Series 3. Draft Case Preparation Binders, 1930
Series 4. Reports, 1890-1930
Series 5. Engineering Studies, 1928-1930
Series 6. Stenographic Notebooks, undated
Series 7. War Department Materials, 1922-1929
Series 8. Correspondence, 1922-1931
Series 9. Subject Files, circa 1900-1932
Series 10. Legislative Files, 1908-1929
Series 11. Press Files, 1926-1930
Series 12. Printed Documents, 1919-1931
Series 13. Invoices, 1928-1931
Series 14. Maps, circa 1913-1930
Related Material
, Connecticut State Library.
, Connecticut State Library.
, Connecticut State Library.
, Connecticut State Library.
, University of Connecticut Libraries Map and Geographic Information Center (MAGIC).
Bibliography
Government Publications
14-16. Hartford: State of Connecticut, 1927-1931.
Articles
“Connecticut v. Massachusetts (282 U.S. 660) Decided February 24, 1931.” The American Journal of International Law 26, no. 1 (January 1932): 163-171.
Simsarian, James. “The Diversion of Interstate Waters in the United States.” The American Political Science Review 32, no. 5 (October 1938): 907-921.
Newspapers
Boston Daily Globe, 1919-1927.
Boston Traveler, 1930.
Bristol (Conn.) Press, 1928.
Hartford Courant, 1924-1931.
Hartford Times, 1928-1930.
Holyoke (Mass.) Transcript, 1928.
Manchester (Conn.) Herald, 1930.
New York Times, 1895-1939.
North Adams (Mass.) Transcript, 1928.
Norwich Bulletin, 1928.
Springfield News, 1928.
Worcester (Mass.) Telegram, 1930.
Websites
Massachusetts Water Resources Authority.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Connecticut. Office of the Attorney General; Water diversion; Water diversion -- Connecticut; Riparian rights -- Connecticut; Water diversion -- Law and legislation; Metropolitan District Water Commission (Mass.); Connecticut. State Water Commission; Massachusetts Water Resources Authority
Places:
Connecticut River; Swift River Valley (Mass.); Connecticut; Massachusetts; Ware River (Mass.); Swift River (Mass.)
Persons:
Callahan, Gerald J.; Alling, Benjamin W.; Healy, Frank E.; Bunn, Charles W.; Averill, Ernest L.; Knowles, Morris; Jacobs, Nathan B.; Davis, Dwight Filley, 1879-1945; Holden, Benedict M.; Cutter, R. Ammi; Cropley, Charles Elmore; McLean, George Payne, 1857-1932; Warner, Joesph E.; Warren, Bentley W.; Winsor, Frank E., 1870-1939
Document Types:
Briefs (legal documents); Clippings; Correspondence; Legal Documents; Maps; Notebooks; Publications; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The Connecticut vs. Massachusetts records from accession T002854 were combined into accession 1994-015.
Container List
- Series 1. Transcripts, 1930-1931
  - Index to volume of testimony; index to testimony; consolidated index to exhibits; qualifications of experts, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings, Volume 1, 1930 February 18; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings, Volume 2, 1930 February 25; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings, Volume 3, 1930 March 3; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings, Volume 4, 1930 March 6; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings, Volume 5, 1930 March 12; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings, Volume 5, 1930 March 18; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings, Volume 6, 1930 March 20; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings, Volume 7, 1930 April 23; 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Corrections to testimony, circa 1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Experience and qualifications of Ezra B. Whitman, 1930 January (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Index to testimony, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous - testimony, 1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oral argument, 1931 January 5-6 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Testimony - index and witness list, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Testimony - rebuttals, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series 2. Exhibits, 1929-1930
  - Book of exhibits, 1929; 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Consolidated index of exhibits, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Exhibits, circa 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Exhibits - C-39, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Exhibits - Hon. E.L. Averill, circa 1910-1930; 1 oversize binder (Box 12)
    The oversize exhibit binder includes exhibits C-4 to C-41 and D-2 to D-37. The binder contains maps, charts, and other graphic materials regarding water flow on the Connecticut River, estimates of potential pollution, and other impacts of water diversion. The end of the binder contains a list and description of the complainants and defendants exhibits.
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series 3. Draft Case Preparation Binders, 1930
  - 1. Massachusetts Project, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 2. Navigation, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - 3. Power, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 4. Agriculture, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 5. Pollution, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 7. Fish Life, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 8. Available Supplies, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 8. Available Supplies, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Stream Flow, undated (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
- Series 4. Reports, 1890-1930
  - Chapter II - Analysis of Legislation and Possibilities of Action Thereunder or Otherwise, 1928 March (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chapter III-A - Stream Flows of Connecticut River and Tributaries, 1928 March (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chapter III-B - Diversion from Connecticut River Tributaries, 1928 March (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chapter V - Pollution in Connecticut River, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chapter VI - Fish Life in Connecticut River, 1928 March (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chapter VIII - Effect of Diversion upon Groud Water Conditions, 1928 March (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chapter X - Necessity for Additional Metropolitan Water Supplies, 1928 March (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chapter XI - Supplies in Eastern Massachussetts, 1928 March (Box 3, Folder 12-16)
  - The Connecticut River Survey, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Development of Unit Prices Water Supply Projects for Boston Metropolitan District, 1928 December 29 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Metropolitan Water and Sewerage Board Thirteenth-Seventeenth Annual Reports, 1913-1917; 5 books (Box 3, Folder 19-23)
  - Metropolitan Water and Sewerage Board Eighteenth Annual Report, 1918; 1 book (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth of Massachusetts Annual Reports of the Metropolitan District Commission, 1924-1926; 3 reports (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
  - Massachussetts State Board of Health Twenty-Second Annual Report, 1890; 1 book (Box 4)